Natalie Spiska: Perfect. If you could just start by talking about what sort of technology you use in your program right now, whether that be, any wearable technology, stats, as well as, like, trackmans or stuff like that?
Coach: So we practice with TrackMan technology, in the winter months, mainly.
Coach: And then we use a STAT program called Circles, which is…
Coach: statistical-driven, but it has an AI component to it that will help players develop based on strengths and opportunities. We call them opportunities, not weaknesses, but…
Coach: You know, the…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: There's a technology component to it,
Coach: And… because it's AI-driven, so… which helps us to identify areas where we can work a little bit, and it… I think it speeds up the learning curve on that.
Natalie Spiska: Is that a new program that you've started to implement?
Coach: We started Circles in the spring of last year.
Coach: You know, It's been a bumpy start to getting players to adapt to that.
Coach: Yeah.
Coach: There's… it's probably the best…
Coach: system on the market in terms of how easy it is, but, you know, I was trying to be sensitive to how players compete.
Coach: and how… You know, there's an element where they have to jot down information, and…
Coach: I didn't want it to be a distraction, but at the same time, I feel like it's important so that we can gather information. A lot of times, as you know.
Coach: you know, at the end of the round, they say, geez, I didn't putt very well. Well, let's think about that. How many 30-footers did you have? You know, like.
Coach: if you're gonna have 30-footers all day long, you're not gonna putt very well. So, you know, that identifies a ball-striking weakness instead of a putting weakness. So you can adapt using technology that way, and I think it speeds up… speeds up the learning curve.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that's… that's super interesting, because I haven't heard of that program yet before, but Clipped is mainly, like, the popular one, and yeah, I definitely understand. Just, like, doing CLIP for a while.
Coach: I'm just gonna interview, sorry.
Natalie Spiska: But, if you can also, since I know that there's also a men's team, is there any difference in that technology, or do you guys use the same, technology?
Coach: We use the same technology for both. The men use the stats program
Coach: And they use the, the, pac-Man technology, also.
Natalie Spiska: Okay, sounds good. And how has the use of technology in your program changed over the last few years?
Coach: Definitely… Skyrocketed how much we use it now.
Coach: But I also still think it's very player-driven.
Coach: I, as an instructor, also…
Coach: I think it's important for me to know the information, but not necessarily the player at all times.
Coach: However, players nowadays are much more in tune with
Coach: the numbers, they're just used to practicing on launch monitors, so they know numbers, and…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: Even, like, our players know numbers, they've grown up using technology, so…
Coach: We use it sparingly at times, and then…
Coach: Heavy at other times, depending on what the player's working on.
Coach: A lot of times, I like to hide the numbers completely.
Coach: So that the player doesn't become so number-driven.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: Ball flight more… Tells the story.
Coach: But sometimes you need to know why the ball flight's not doing what you're expecting it to do, and technology really, really helps in that regard.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that sort of touches on my next question, which is if there's any particular skill area that you think technology's been most beneficial to use it in. Like, if that's ball striking, putting, short game.
Coach: Definitely ball striking.
Coach: You know, with the ball flight laws, coming into light a lot more, you know, as an instructor, the technology, or the technical information
Coach: Of why the ball curves, and why the ball starts, and…
Coach: all that stuff has really skyrocketed over the last couple years, and I feel like… that information…
Coach: Has come to light by the use of technology.
Coach: A lot more, and a lot quicker, really quick.
Coach: And do you think…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah? You can fish it, go ahead.
Coach: The thought is that instruction in the last 10 years has probably gone quicker Than the previous 30 years.
Coach: You know, so that technologies really just help speed up the learning curve on that.
Natalie Spiska: And do you think there's a particular, like, personality type of your student athletes that finds technology more beneficial, or do you think it's the same across the board? Like, everyone benefits the same way?
Coach: I think players benefit the same way.
Coach: just different methods.
Natalie Spiska: So…
Coach: By having the… the ball flight technology,
Coach: They're… whether they use it and understand it completely, or they're using the instructor's knowledge.
Coach: They're using it and getting better quicker.
Coach: And…
Coach: I feel like…
Coach: that nowadays, with players used to the growing up with technology, I feel like they're more in tune with what it is. When it first came out, the Trackman first came out, I think people were intimidated by the fact that the numbers… they didn't understand the numbers, they didn't know…
Coach: how to utilize the numbers, how to improve quicker. I think that part…
Coach: It was intimidating at first, but now that intimidation factor's gone now.
Coach: So I think… I still think the personality of the player If they're more analytical.
Coach: They're going to be wanting to know what the numbers are. If they're more of a field player, they're going to want to see the ball flight curve the way they want to see it.
Coach: But then they might be curious enough to say, okay, now, why is it curving this way?
Coach: The analytical player will want to know every number, every swing, and that gets a little dangerous sometimes.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I was gonna ask, do you ever worry that your players are gonna, like, get too lost in the numbers? Because I definitely have been there in the past, where I'm like, I need to just not look at any numbers right now and just swing normally.
Coach: Yeah, I do think that, you know, I grew up as a field player myself.
Coach: So, I think the numbers, although I appreciate the numbers, I would have been a kind of a hide-the-numbers type of player.
Coach: And use them when I need them. I get worried when a player
Coach: Hits a shot, goes to the monitor, hits a shot, goes to the monitor, and we're constantly, you know, trying to do something. It's…
Coach: I think that that becomes detrimental, like, if… let's use that when we have a problem. If you're seeing the ball the way you want it to see, and you're intending to do this, we don't need to be trying to fix every golf swing.
Coach: And I feel like sometimes the natural feel of a player Gets impacted by too much.
Natalie Spiska: I can, yeah, I can definitely agree with that, where sometimes the ball on screen, the flight is good, and it looks good, but if a certain number's off, you're like, it's not a good shot, when in reality, it is. Like, it'll work on the golf course. No pictures on the scorecard, so…
Coach: No, and… and to me, the… trying to…
Coach: get the path and the face to zero out. That was a thing there for a while, and I think players have kind of stopped trying to chase that perfect number.
Coach: Because the ball flight, you know, it's not gonna go…
Coach: Exactly as intended every single time anyway.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah. And then trying to change the golf swing based on.
Coach: Swing 1 and swing 10, it's a little bit, you can be chasing things that don't need to be chased at that point in time.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I've… I can definitely relate to that, for sure.
Natalie Spiska: Are there any technologies that you've tried to use, and then you ended up not using it? And it was… was there any reason for that?
Coach: Not yet. I think that for me, right now, expense on some Things has held us back.
Coach: Yeah. Honestly.
Coach: Like, would it be… Super interesting to have force plates.
Coach: On every swing.
Coach: I think it would be, but the expense of having those and how much I would use them…
Coach: Is kind of a… you're at a crossroads there of what technology to introduce at that point.
Coach: But I'm a curious kind of instructor and curious kind of coach in the sense that I want to try to figure out, like, how can I make my players better?
Coach: And what kind of technology could I… Institute.
Coach: At the same time, similar to stats.
Coach: I feel like sometimes that gets in the way of the player's progress.
Coach: If we're trying to introduce too many things, and the player resists.
Coach: I think we kind of take a step back at that point, too. So I'm careful of how much we introduce and how much we bring into things. I try to go slow and introduce it.
Coach: Not as to distract the player.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that's… I feel like that's a good method to employ, just to make sure that, once again, you don't exactly overload, and once again, you're surrounded by all these numbers, and you're like, oh no, everything's broken, when in reality, it's usually not.
Coach: Yeah, and I think that that's something that technology has just made us so much smarter, but at the same time, it…
Coach: you can see the wheels spinning a lot of times, too, and I think that that…
Coach: Golf is such a feel game, I think, you're better off…
Coach: using it when you need to. And then, you know, you know how it is in the Northeast with…
Coach: trying to get better in the months where you can't get outside, I think that's when it's super important. And I don't think that…
Coach: you know, we're going to [State] tomorrow,
Coach: you know, I don't have portable… technology, so…
Coach: you know, we'll just be seeing the ball go in the air at that point, and I think that all the work that we've done with technology now will help us going forward, so…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah. Are there any types of performance tools or insights that you wish existed but don't yet?
Natalie Spiska: Or, if you can't think of anything, you sort of touched on it a little bit, is there any sort of technology that you wish you could get for your program?
Coach: I do think, more in the terms of putting technology.
Coach: Sam Putt Lab… Putt view, where the…
Coach: the overview.
Natalie Spiska: It goes up and down.
Coach: Yeah, I think that that kind of… technology.
Coach: Into the indoor game, because now the indoor game has so much…
Coach: improved in the last even 3 years compared to what it used to be. And the ability to, you know, we used to just pop up a net in the gymnasium.
Coach: 10… hit 10, 15 swings, and then switch, you know, and that…
Coach: That now has exploded into a different… everybody has their own bay, everybody has a trackman, and so that kind of technology advancement has really skyrocketed, and…
Coach: I think plotting would be the next thing for me, what we would want to try to
Coach: Yeah, because putting is so important, and…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: And we just don't spend a whole lot of time on that indoors, particularly.
Coach: But, at the same time, putting is a feel aspect that's really feel.
Coach: And technology there could be detrimental, but I do think there's a lot of really good technology that we could use in the short game that we don't currently have.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I especially agree with the putting. It's hard to switch from being indoors, especially… we have, like, sort of like a flat green here that can go up and down, but…
Coach: Okay.
Natalie Spiska: it's definitely, like, the green speed's really fast, and we were down in Florida, and the greens are super slow, and suddenly you're like, well, what are we gonna do? We were practicing for fast greens, and now we have slow greens, so…
Coach: It's always a mixed bag, especially up in the Northeast, I feel like.
Coach: It's, you know, putting from… I… because I think that, you know, even if you're at a
Coach: Place that has fast greens, depending on where your ball is, if you're above the hole, below the hole…
Coach: You've got curvature, you've got length…
Natalie Spiska: Yep.
Coach: every green's really different, so you have to be able to adapt, and I think that that's where technology could speed that up a little bit.
Coach: Where you, on one point, you could hit a really severe uphill putt and a really severe downhill putt.
Coach: And be able to quickly learn The stroke tendencies on that.
Coach: So I do think that there's technology In the short game that…
Coach: we don't currently utilize that I think would be hugely beneficial.
Natalie Spiska: I just have a few more questions for you. What role do you think technology will play in college golf in the next 5 to 10 years, and if you think that'll impact the recruiting process in any way?
Coach: I think it's going to go light speed, yes.
Coach: It's going to go crazy, because now…
Coach: You're really seeing young players that we're recruiting now
Coach: that every day are using technology. So this… and I think that that's going to impact recruiting, because
Coach: If they're using it in their own game and we don't have it.
Coach: That might cause a player to go to a different school if…
Coach: we don't have what they're already used to having.
Coach: And you can see that with some players now, and I think COVID changed that, where…
Coach: The… the players now that are…
Coach: freshmen, seniors in high school, juniors in high school, all grew up using technology, so I… to answer that, and I… it's going to go…
Coach: Light speed fast. And we're gonna, we're gonna have to really adapt.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I've…
Natalie Spiska: I've spoken to a few other coaches, and they've all agreed with that as well, where in the recruiting process especially, all of these young golfers that are coming through are so much more used to technology, and they're using it in their everyday. So, yeah, it'll be interesting to see where it ends up in a few years even.
Coach: The next thing that I'm interested in using
Coach: technology for, too, that I think is going to be part of how fast this goes is physical fitness.
Natalie Spiska: Hmm, yeah.
Coach: And how players adapt to exercise and workouts.
Coach: and using… AI is a little intimidating.
Coach: But I do think that there's a lot of… instances where AI…
Coach: Is going to really change how players work out, how they… how their body feels after an event,
Coach: And then being able to recover quickly.
Coach: And then… used… Things like technology to get better speed-wise.
Natalie Spiska: Hmm.
Coach: We're seeing it a little bit, and I… I don't know…
Coach: If it would be considered technology, but, we use Golf Forever.
Coach: Which is the program that Scotty Scheffler uses to warm up.
Natalie Spiska: Hm, yes. Okay.
Coach: It's the… it's resistance bands, it's stretching,
Coach: And we utilize videos, but it can be tailored from player to player based on their physical fitness ability.
Coach: So that's where I think technology… That's going to explode.
Coach: to where… The individual workouts.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah?
Coach: The individual workout's going to be tailored exactly to what you need, whether it's hip mobility, ankle mobility, core strength.
Coach: That's gonna be driven directly to you.
Coach: So you can watch a 15-minute video, and do a workout in your dorm room, and…
Coach: you know, that's gonna just be amazing. I think players are gonna be way more ready to play high-level tournament golf because of that.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Natalie Spiska: especially with the AI analysis system that you mentioned, like, how would that work in, like, a fitness setting? Like, it analyzes you, and it tells you if your form is correct, or… is that sort of it?
Coach: I think it's… I think the… the canvas is clear. I think what you can do with AI in terms of…
Coach: Not only just answering
Coach: But then maybe even being able to physically watch a movement, whether it's, you know, watching a golf swing and then saying, wow, you know.
Coach: And… To a certain extent, when you look at video now, you can…
Coach: You know, how much of the hip turn is…
Coach: being utilized? How much of a sway is going back and forth? You… you can already see some of that stuff,
Coach: And then you program that into AI, where they say, okay, 4-degree hip movement this direction is, you know, we need to do this, because that looks like it's not…
Coach: physically right.
Coach: And…
Natalie Spiska: I think it could be…
Coach: really, that physical fitness, I think, could really go in a…
Coach: Really high direction, going forward.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I definitely think so as well. Overall, this is my final question, overall, would you say technology's had a positive or negative impact on your program?
Coach: Very positive.
Natalie Spiska: Is it?
Coach: Yeah, I think that players are better. I mean, you see it now in competitions. I mean, it…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: You're a senior now, you've…
Coach: competed for 4 years, and you can see freshmen coming into programs now that are instantly able to compete.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: That… four years ago wasn't the case, you know? There were special talents then, but not…
Coach: as I think it's just way more… Advanced now, and… and…
Coach: As you see recruits coming in.
Coach: those players are more advanced, and so technology, I think, has been a huge positive.
Natalie Spiska: Alright, perfect. I will stop recording right now.